Guide to the Tomlinson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Tomlinson family papers
1758-1865
MS 1172
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Correspondence, financial records, and legal documents of the Tomlinson and related families of Connecticut. Prominent in the correspondence are six letters (1826-1853) by Gideon Tomlinson, governor of Connecticut (1826-1831) and a series of Civil War letters (1862-1865) by Albert DeForest of the 14th Connecticut Volunteers. Also a farming diary (1793-1805) kept probably by Joel Beard of Stratford, and the daybook (1805-1812) of Curtiss Tomlinson, a farmer of Huntington. Additional account books include one kept (1843-1848) by Gideon Tomlinson for the account of Mrs. Clarina Brewster, and another kept by Stephen Tomlinson, a dyer of Stratford, from 1814 to 1845.
Tomlinson family
Scope and Contents
The Tomlinson Family Papers, which focus on several Tomlinsons and related families from the Stratford, Connecticut area, are housed in one box (18 folders).
Folders 1-6 contain correspondence. The two chief correspondents are Gideon Tomlinson (1780-1854) and Albert DeForest. Tomlinson was a congressman 1819-1827, governor of Connecticut 1827-1831, and senator 1831-1837. The papers contain six letters by and to him, the most important being letters from Tomlinson to Nathan Smith (1770-1835) 1826 Apr 4 discussing a political appointment and from Ingoldsby W. Crawford (1786-1867) 1835 Feb 25 refuting charges of irregularity in the building of the New London customs house. The second major correspondent, Albert DeForest, served in the 14th Connecticut Volunteers during the Civil War from 1862-1865. DeForest was not well educated but served his regiment well, beginning as a private and ending a lieutenant. He writes to his uncle and aunt, Mr. and Mrs. Philo Birdseye of Stratford. Included in the correspondence are four other letters, written by Diodate Silliman in 1782, Augustus Tomlinson and his son Mark Tomlinson in 1863, and by Charles A. Hatch in 1864.
The remaining papers primarily concern three generations of Tomlinsons. The chief figures are Gideon Tomlinson (-1765) of Stratford, grandfather of the Connecticut governor; Jabez Huntington Tomlinson (1760-1849), father of the governor; Captain Joseph Tomlinson (-1774), brother of Gideon; his son Curtiss Tomlinson; and Stephen Tomlinson (1791-), son of Curtiss. Several documents and a court case relate to fishing rights for Curtiss Tomlinson. The papers also include unidentified diaries for 1793, 1800, and 1805 by a Stratford region farmer.
Biographical / Historical
Gideon Tomlinson was born in Fairfield County, Connecticut on December 31, 1780. He was the son of Jabez H. and Rebecca (Lewis) Tomlinson. Jabez Huntington Tomlinson was a student at Yale and, in 1779, was captured by a party of British raiders and taken to New York. On his release he entered the army. Governor Gideon Tomlinson graduated from Yale College in 1802, then studied law, finally making his home in Fairfield. He was a member of congress between 1819-1827, and then became the eighth governor of Connecticut (1827-31). He resigned the governorship to enter the United States Senate. He was married to Sarah Bradley, and had two sons. He died October 8, 1854.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Agriculture -- Connecticut; Families; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Politics and government; Account books; Diaries; Farmers; Public officers; Soldiers; Beard, Joel, 1765-1846; Brewster, Clarina Bradley; Crawford, Ingoldsby Work, 1786-1867; DeForest, Albert; Tomlinson, Curtiss, fl. 1779-1832; Tomlinson, Gideon, 1780-1854; Tomlinson, Jabez Huntington, 1760-1849; Tomlinson, Stephen, b. 1791; Tomlinson family; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 14th (1862-1865)
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The Tomlinson Family Papers are arranged by subject in order of relative importance. In each of the 18 folders, materials are placed in chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1826-53 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Deeds, 1758-1812 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Indenture, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fishing Rights, 1786-1815 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Court Papers, 1819-20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bills, receipts, 1770-95 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bills, receipts, 1797-1825, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Accounts: Gideon Tomlinson and Mrs. Clarina Brewster, 1843-48 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Accounts, miscellaneous, 1787-1822 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Day book: Curtiss Tomlinson, 1805-12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ledger: Stephen Tomlinson, 1814-45 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Biographical material on Jabez Huntington Tomlinson, as related to Charles H. Booth in 1840: typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified diaries Stratford area (attributed to Joel Beard), 1793, 1800, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 18)